<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter to a gentleman in the commission of the peace exciting him to the performance of his part in executing the late act against profane cursing and swearing.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48181</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9542792</idno>
  <idno type="VID">43562</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264196919</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26782</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09542792</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1335:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter to a gentleman in the commission of the peace exciting him to the performance of his part in executing the late act against profane cursing and swearing.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>76, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Swearing --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43562:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43562:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO A GENTLEMAN In the <hi>Commission of the Peace,</hi> Exciting him to the PERFORMANCE of his PART IN Executing the late ACT Against <hi>Profane Cursing and Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON▪</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke▪</hi> at the <hi>Middle Temple Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetstr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43562:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43562:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A Gentleman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR last Favours added to all the former were so greatly Obliging, That I could not let slip this Opportunity of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing the grateful Sence I have of such <hi>Generous</hi> Kindness: 'Tis a humility more than common that makes you so Condes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending to Inferiors, and a Goodness which sets you off more than all your <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Fortune,</hi> that you study the ways of Pleasing the Lovers of Ingenuity and Piety with some Agreeable Entertainments. And by your Admiring and Praising such an excellent <hi>Design,</hi> as you were pleased to Communicate last time I had occasion to be your Guest; you much Commend your own acute Judgment, and your good Relish
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43562:3"/> of that which the <hi>Illiterate</hi> Scorn, and the <hi>Prophane</hi> Abhor. May you go on Sir, (so befitting your <hi>Quality</hi>) to delight your self in such worthy Studies; for which all good men will join with me to Honour and applaud you. It would be great pity Sir, if one accomplished with such Gifts of Nature, improved with <hi>Polite</hi> Learning, and Sweetness of Manners, and who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your self so <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd for that which is Right and Good, As also so much in the Interest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Government, (if you) should not be found <hi>Consistent</hi> with your self, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, your Goodness all of a <hi>Peice.</hi> But as much as I was pleas'd with all your other Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and carriage, in which you were kind to impart your self so <hi>Free</hi> and open: yet I must take the boldness to tell you Sir, That I was not a little <hi>Surpris'd</hi> at one thing which dropt from your Lips, and sent m away not so well satisfied as I could have wish'd, out of your Company. And it was this, That you who so readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd with me, in Condemning the Folly and Wickedness of <hi>Common Swearing,</hi> and its Mischeivousness to the <hi>Publick,</hi> as well as to a mans own <hi>Soul</hi> (So that you have made it unnecessary for me to take any pains to Convince you of the Sin and Evil) should, for all this not shew your self very
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43562:3"/> well pleased, but rather somewhat aggriev'd at the late <hi>Act,</hi> for the more effectual sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing of <hi>Prophane Cursing and Swearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An <hi>Act</hi> which so many Wise and Good Men thought highly <hi>Needful</hi> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, and not a little rejoyce to see it accomplish'd. That the notorious Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God and Godliness should <hi>Droop</hi> and be <hi>Sullen</hi> upon it, who can wonder? For this is but to appear in their own <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> But it seems to me strangely unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable, Sir, That any Ingenious Good Man should not be Glad with all his heart, to hear of any <hi>Remedy</hi> devis'd to help us against such a Crying and Prevailing Sin, such a Senseless and Odious Wickedness. If I understood you aright Sir, and if you spoke not what you did only by way of <hi>Objection,</hi> as Tempting me to express my Sense of the matter; I cannot Imagin what should be the Cause of your <hi>Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardness</hi> to comply with such an excellent Means, at least, to Restrain, if not quite to Cure, this <hi>Rampant</hi> Ungodliness: Unless it be some of the following <hi>Considerations,</hi> which (now you have left me to Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) I shall name, and (in the familiar way you have embolden'd me to speak) give you my thoughts of, <hi>viz.</hi> your Des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair of doing any <hi>Good.</hi> Your Tenderness
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43562:4"/> of <hi>Disobliging</hi> your Friends. Your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingness to Spoil <hi>Company.</hi> Or your Fear of Creating your self <hi>Trouble;</hi> or of getting <hi>Ill-will:</hi> or to be censured for <hi>Singular, Precise,</hi> or a <hi>Busie-Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First then, Sir, Are you so loath to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern your self in pursuance of the Design of this <hi>Act,</hi> because Hopeless of doing any Good, to Regulate a Disorder so <hi>Inveterate,</hi> and generally Prevalent; 'till 'tis grown even the <hi>Fashion</hi> of the Age? Do you think it Vain therefore to strive against the Stream, and as good do nothing as to no purpose: when the thing is past Cure, and so sets all Remedies at <hi>Defiance;</hi> that no <hi>Healing</hi> can be expected? I heartily Bewail it, Sir, That there should be so much <hi>Occasion</hi> for this Objection. Though my Calling and Course of Life (I bless God), sets me much out of the way of the <hi>Dammes,</hi> and mad <hi>Hectors</hi> of our Times; and so I may hear but the <hi>Parsons</hi> part of their Blasphemies: yet in every corner as I pass I am often Witness to so much as makes me fear the Corruption to be <hi>Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical,</hi> and the World so <hi>Incurably</hi> Evil, That I may as soon make account to stop <hi>Severn</hi> with my hand, as to put a <hi>Non ultra</hi> to the Course of its Wickedness. However most Passengers through this World, seem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43562:4"/> they are bound for the Joys of the next; We may guess too well by the <hi>Throng,</hi> that the greater number take the <hi>Broadway.</hi> And where Offenders are so exceeding Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, Rulers sometimes have thought it Advisable to make their <hi>Multitudes</hi> an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of their <hi>Indemnity,</hi> and let them Escape, as too many to be Punished. 'Tis a <hi>Maxime</hi> indeed, <hi>Nemo tenetur ad Impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibile,</hi> you are not bound Sir, to Reform all the World.</p>
            <p>Yet where you cannot do every thing, as you <hi>would,</hi> that will not excuse you from doing what you <hi>can.</hi> If the <hi>Whole</hi> is not to be sav'd, yet 'tis a Praise worthy Attempt to do somewhat <hi>towards</hi> it, and save as much as may be, yea though you can Effect nothing to your Mind, yet 'tis a great deal but to shew your <hi>Good-will</hi> Sir, and so to Deliver your own <hi>Soul.</hi> And you have not Labour'd in vain, nor Spent your strength for nought, though <hi>Israel</hi> be not Gather'd: as long as your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is with the <hi>Lord,</hi> and your Work with your <hi>God. (Isa.</hi> 49.4, 5.) you shall be never the less Glorious in his Eyes, for your very <hi>Desire</hi> to bring him Glory. And he will Reward you, not according to the <hi>Success,</hi> but according to your <hi>Aims</hi> and <hi>Endeavours</hi> to promote his Honor and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43562:5"/> Pleasure. And oh how much more might be done, Sir, than is done, this way? The <hi>Lazy</hi> and <hi>Ill affected</hi> cry, They shall make <hi>Nothing</hi> of it: When indeed they have no <hi>Mind</hi> to it. But would every one thus lay out the Power and Interest which they have, soon might we see a mighty <hi>Change</hi> in the World much for the better. And such as have been <hi>Outragious,</hi> would at least be more <hi>Mannerly,</hi> with their Wickedness. Would you Sir, but heartily Espouse the Cause of God's Honor, and shew your self <hi>Vigorous</hi> for it, as far as your <hi>Influence</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, O what a Blessing would it be to your Family, and your Neighbourhood? And how much Good might you do Sir, in being, but (as you ought to be) <hi>a Terror to the Evil-doers?</hi> For, alas, they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to say for themselves, but what one would be ashamed to hear. There is nothing but a silly and ungodly <hi>Custom</hi> on their side: when <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> and all the <hi>Laws</hi> of God and Man are clear against them. Methinks then it may be to some purpose to take up the <hi>Cudgels,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with 'em. And where you cannot <hi>Gain</hi> 'em, yet 'tis worth while to <hi>Confound</hi> 'em. That they may not be so <hi>Impudent,</hi> when discover'd to be quite in the <hi>Wrong:</hi> Nor in such danger to <hi>Infect</hi> and Poyson others, when under <hi>Correction</hi> and Publick <hi>Disgrace</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43562:5"/> themselves. 'Tis from <hi>Impunity</hi> that they take so much Boldness, and therefore Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment must needs be some Restraint. But if you hear them Swear or Curse, and <hi>Connive</hi> or Laugh at 'em, you thus bid 'em Sin on, and make them <hi>Proud</hi> of the Office to give you such Diversion, and make your <hi>Worship</hi> so Merry. Hence the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Wretches are ready to infer, not only, that there's small <hi>Hurt</hi> in it, but that 'tis their Honor and Interest, and they do <hi>Well</hi> to be so <hi>Wicked.</hi> And thus, I am sure, you may do Infinite <hi>Mischief,</hi> Sir, when in your self you betray any thing like a <hi>Prophane</hi> humour, and a wretched <hi>Contempt</hi> of Gods Honor: which Mischief certainly, Sir, you may and ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. And even in doing so much, you will do us no small Good. And did all such as you, who set the <hi>Fashion</hi> to so many others, but Frown upon the Swearing <hi>Crew,</hi> and shew your Abhorrence of that which our <hi>Senators</hi> justly call the <hi>Detestable Sin;</hi> This must needs Contribute a great deal to the Beating of it down. Would you never <hi>Scowl</hi> and look Awry at Sobriety and the Fear of God, to dash it out of <hi>Countenance;</hi> but approve your self in good <hi>Earnest</hi> for it, and make them know, you would never endure to hear it Scorn'd and <hi>Ridicul'd;</hi> Thus your <hi>Example</hi> would help
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43562:6"/> to bring it into greater Repute, and oblige them to keep a better <hi>Decorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further yet might you go, Sir, by your <hi>Authority,</hi> in doing according to the Obligation now lying upon you, to put the <hi>Act</hi> against Swearing in <hi>Execution:</hi> and let none Escape that make themselves Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious in your <hi>Presence,</hi> and to your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. And so far should the <hi>Commonness</hi> of the Evil be from Discouraging any to Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it, That it should but the more Awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken every good Christians <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Mettle</hi> to do what ever in them lyes, to give some Check to the Spreading <hi>Plague:</hi> That, at least a <hi>Remnant</hi> may be Heal'd and Sav'd: and not <hi>all</hi> Ruin'd and Lost.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>Council</hi> of this Land, you see, Sir, did not, from the <hi>Inefficacy</hi> of former Means; take Excuse to <hi>Supersede</hi> any further Attempts, but rather a <hi>Provocation,</hi> to try somewhat afresh, and to <hi>Enact</hi> a Stricter <hi>Law,</hi> enforced with bigger <hi>Penalties:</hi> Which their Wisdom judges may help to <hi>Suppress</hi> the Wickedness. Now that it is to be bought at a Dearer rate than ever; And they have so <hi>Stigmatized</hi> the Swearers, and made them go in <hi>Gyves</hi> and <hi>Fetters.</hi> And God knows what may be done by this means well pursued: If <hi>Witnesses</hi> and <hi>Magistrates</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:43562:6"/> be not shamefully wanting in their Office O be not hopeless then Sir, nor Heartless to do your <hi>Part:</hi> And leave the <hi>Issue</hi> to his <hi>Blessing,</hi> who uses to smile upon all such Pious <hi>Designs,</hi> how many soever in this Wicked World look awry at 'em.</p>
            <p>Secondly. Are you Tender of <hi>Disobli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> your Friends, and therefore shy to meddle, lest you should be thought <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind?</hi> Indeed, Sir, Friendship is a <hi>Sacred</hi> Bond, which every Good Man will be afraid to <hi>violate.</hi> But if the doing of <hi>Justice,</hi> and discharging a necessary Duty, must make a Breach of Friendship; I much question whether we ought to be very <hi>Scrupulous</hi> in keeping up such a Friendship. And I cannot think we are Oblig'd to please any <hi>Friends,</hi> at the Hazard of <hi>God</hi>'s Displeasure. But must rather be in Care to <hi>Honor</hi> our God, than to <hi>Humour</hi> our Friend. You know, Sir, what an <hi>Honourable</hi> and Excellent Person says in the case,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Bosom Friend, if he Blaspheme thy Name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will tear thence his Love and Fame.</hi>
                     <bibl>Herb.</bibl>
                  </l>
               </q> When such as bear the <hi>Character</hi> of our Friends will be so Unkind to their own Souls, to List themselves among <hi>Gods Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43562:7"/> (and who they are you are told, <hi>Psalm.</hi> 139.20. <hi>Thy Enemies take thy Name in Vain</hi>) The Example of that Man after <hi>Gods Heart</hi> will warrant you to count them your <hi>Enemies.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>i. e.</hi> As far as they are against the <hi>Lord,</hi> to be utterly against them in so <hi>ill a way:</hi> and to shew more <hi>Faithfulness</hi> to him, than to <hi>Comply</hi> with such as Provoke and dare him, even to his Face. But that which looks so <hi>Disobliging</hi> to them, may yet verily, be one of the greatest <hi>Courtesies</hi> you could do 'em: For Good Sir, what true Friendship have you for that man whose reall <hi>Happiness</hi> you desire not? And how can you Love your Friend, and not care for his <hi>Soul</hi> (which is his very Self) though it be <hi>Lost</hi> for ever? Is that Hearty Love, To <hi>Hate your Brother in your Heart?</hi> And if you <hi>Suffer</hi> the Sin which you see upon him, what better is it? <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. Is any one a better <hi>Friend,</hi> nearer or Dearer to you than your <hi>Lord and your God?</hi> Must you give up his <hi>Honour,</hi> to Gratifie anothers wicked <hi>Pleasure?</hi> And are you so <hi>Great</hi> with them, that you will <hi>Sacrifice</hi> your Religion and Gods Glory to 'em? Or are you so <hi>Bound</hi> to them that you must <hi>Despise</hi> him, and <hi>Pawn</hi> your Soul to do them a <hi>Kindness?</hi> But I pray you, Sir, can you indeed think it a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to <hi>Embolden</hi> them in the way to Hell?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43562:7"/> And that they are so much <hi>Beholden</hi> to you, for excusing them from a little <hi>Penalty,</hi> which might help to deliver them from everlasting <hi>Misery?</hi> Not that I think such a pitiful Sum can be the <hi>Price</hi> of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: But as a <hi>Warning-piece,</hi> it may be a means to make them more <hi>Cautious</hi> in keeping off from the Wickedness, which bodes no better than their <hi>Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Loose</hi> Lives make the <hi>Fast</hi> Friends, soon and sad will be the <hi>End</hi> of all that Friendship; when as the <hi>Brotherhood</hi> in Iniquity are only Combined in a <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy</hi> against the Heavenly Majesty: and such <hi>Holding</hi> together will at last come to downright <hi>Cursing</hi> one another. We ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the very mention of a mans felling his Soul to the <hi>Devil:</hi> But, Good Sir, what Softer Name does that <hi>League</hi> and Friendship deserve, when a man must give up the <hi>Kings</hi> Laws, and <hi>Gods</hi> Glory, and his own <hi>Conscience,</hi> and Everlasting <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> all to spare and favour a mad Hellish <hi>Swearer?</hi> If you take some of that <hi>Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> for your Friends, O be not then too Cruel to them, Sir, as to let them run on in their cursed <hi>Enmity</hi> to God, and lie unmolested in the Paws of the <hi>Devil.</hi> Tho they might peradventure give you more <hi>Thanks</hi> to let 'em alone as they are:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43562:8"/> You are not to seek their Thanks, Sir, so much as their <hi>Salvation.</hi> And could you but any way, be Instrumental to <hi>Break</hi> them of the Damning Wickedness, you would Oblige them <hi>Eternally.</hi> Tho now they may be Stomachful at you, they would have cause for ever to Thank and Bless you. Never fear then thus to <hi>Lose</hi> your friends, Sir, For this is the way to <hi>Gain</hi> them, and to make them the Fastest Friends World without end.</p>
            <p>But if your Charity be so excessive, Sir, you think you must be <hi>Unreasonably</hi> Kind to your Friend, How can you so forget the <hi>Poor,</hi> as to give away their <hi>Portion,</hi> and never Stick to Rob them of the Relief, which the same <hi>Law</hi> whereby you hold all that you have, makes due to them? Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks you should also Shrink at this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness and Cruelty, this Fraud and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury: And not let your fond <hi>Indulgence</hi> to a carnal Friend eat up your tender <hi>Compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> towards Gods Poor: Nor be kind to your Friend, with that which is none of your own, but <hi>Theirs.</hi> And though you are not to Rejoyce at this <hi>Occasion</hi> of their Relief, Yet neither must you stand in the way, to stop it from them, when by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> it falls to 'em.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43562:8"/>
            <p>Thirdly. Are you loath to Spoil <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> and therefore you Interrupt not the <hi>Swearers</hi> that are some of the <hi>Jolliest</hi> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, least you should seem <hi>Morose</hi> and Ill humour'd? The <hi>Cherefulness</hi> of Society, I confess, Sir, it is the Sweetest <hi>Sawce</hi> of Humane Life: And I should be as back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as any to <hi>Upbraid</hi> the Innocent <hi>Mirth</hi> and Pleasantness of Conversation. But methinks 'tis very hard, Sir, if men cannot be <hi>Pleasant,</hi> but they must be <hi>Prophane:</hi> if it must quite <hi>Marre</hi> the Meeting, to be <hi>Merry and Wise:</hi> And no joy till they <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> themselves, and turn Bruits or Fiends, to toss and bandy in Blasphemous Mouths the Ever-Blessed <hi>Name</hi> for a Pastime: and Powder their <hi>Games</hi> with Florid Oaths and Spice their <hi>Cups</hi> with more of the same: Not knowing how to be <hi>Chearful,</hi> without being <hi>Mad,</hi> and because the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor pleases 'em, Pelt the Name of <hi>God,</hi> to pay him so for the Comfort. I believe, Sir, you may not be a Stranger to some, that would count themselves Dull and <hi>Melancholy,</hi> as a parcel of <hi>Mop'd Fools,</hi> where all the <hi>Quickness</hi> of Conceit, and the very <hi>Life</hi> of Conversation is gone, when they are under such a Confinement, that there must be no <hi>Swearing,</hi> for fear of the <hi>Penalty.</hi> But I pray you, Sir, were not all Men so confined before this <hi>New
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43562:9"/> Law,</hi> under a far more dreadful <hi>Penalty</hi> than any now Imposed in the <hi>Act?</hi> Sure their Tongues were never so their own, but by their <hi>Words they were to be Justified, and by their Words to be Condemned.</hi> And if this Spoil the Pleasure of any Society, O how well does that <hi>Mirth</hi> deserve to be so <hi>Marred?</hi> where Lewd Companions can make no <hi>Sport,</hi> but they must make God himself the Subject of their <hi>Drollery,</hi> and <hi>Swear</hi> away their God, and their Souls, and the best of all their Friends? The serious Remembrance of their Lord and Judge would strike such Rebels into their Dumps: and therefore they love to <hi>Play</hi> with the Being of God, as an Empty <hi>Name,</hi> to <hi>Swear</hi> by it, without <hi>Believing</hi> in it. yea their Customary Swearing by it, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es them Still more to <hi>Slight</hi> and despise it: As if the God, whom they so often and <hi>Absurdly</hi> Appeal to, were but a Name for <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to turn the <hi>Stream</hi> of such Corrupt and abominable Communication, is the greatest Kindness to all the <hi>Company:</hi> That they may not go on so to Hew down themselves, and sadden the Souls of some, and Harden the Hearts of others. For were that which is so extremely <hi>Noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some</hi> and intolerably <hi>Offensive</hi> to God and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43562:9"/> all Good Men but once <hi>Wedded</hi> out of their Conversation; As they could not but be much Easier to themselves at the bottom, so would they take off the Infamous <hi>Brand</hi> from their Names, and Recommend their society to the Servants of God, who before fled it, as their <hi>Nuisance</hi> and Horror.</p>
            <p>I cannot but admire, Sir, if one of your Accomplishments should not perfectly Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the <hi>Ruffianly</hi> Company that make <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Curses</hi> their Game and Musick, and are not in their <hi>Element,</hi> till the place that holds 'em, become as the <hi>Mouth of Hell;</hi> full of such Blasphemies and <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations,</hi> as would drive away any Serious Christian, that had the Calamity to be cast upon 'em, and send him to go and seek out a nother <hi>Air</hi> to breath in. You know better things, Sir, and are fit to keep better <hi>Company.</hi> Twill be your Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then and Honor, either to Break off from 'em, or so Carry among 'em, as shall make them afraid and weary to do so Foolishly, and Wickedly: and thus really approve your self one of the most kind and Compassionate men, and even as a <hi>Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Angel,</hi> and their Good <hi>Genius,</hi> shed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an <hi>Auspicious</hi> Influence, to make all about you the better for you.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43562:10"/>
            <p>Fourthly. Are you afraid, Sir, of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your self <hi>Trouble,</hi> by Encountring such Offenders, the <hi>Wild Beasts</hi> that are so apt to Kick and Bite; and not like to Spare any Men, when they no more Care even for the <hi>Most-High?</hi> And therefore though you cannot Approve of 'em yet for your own <hi>Ease,</hi> you Wink at 'em? I have a greater Esteem for you, Sir, than to push you upon the <hi>Pikes,</hi> where you might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sit still and be <hi>Quiet.</hi> I wish they were out of the way, that so much <hi>Trouble</hi> you and the World. And I only desire you may take the course to prevent farther <hi>Trouble</hi> with them for the future: Or if they continue to be Troublesome, I would so <hi>Fortifie</hi> you against them, that you may-not stand in Awe of 'em. And I would direct you to such a Noble <hi>Pleasure,</hi> in the brave Discharge of your Place, as shall more than <hi>Countervail</hi> for all the Trouble which comes from that Quarter.</p>
            <p>You know, Sir, there is some <hi>Difficulty</hi> in every thing that is <hi>Praise-Worthy:</hi> And he must never think of <hi>Heaven,</hi> that will not <hi>Strive to Enter at the Streight Gate.</hi> Such as are all for the <hi>Easy</hi> way are in no good likelyhood for the Blessed <hi>End.</hi> And why are you <hi>Advanced</hi> above others, but that you should do <hi>More</hi> than others? your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43562:10"/> Wealth and your Honor was not given you that you should indulge to your Sloath and your Lust: But the more Promote his <hi>Glory</hi> who has put you in such a <hi>Capacity:</hi> And thereby obliged you to do the Nobler and Greater Service to God and men. If you shrink at the <hi>Burden,</hi> you are unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the <hi>Honor.</hi> When the Giver of all Good has put enough into your Possession, to defray your <hi>Charge,</hi> and you have a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> even in hand, as well as infinitely Better to Expect, if you well acquit your self. And the more you do, Sir, but the <hi>better</hi> still will it be for your self, as well as for others. You know, the man of God's own Approbation, was not for serving the Lord his God with that which <hi>Cost him No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> 2. Sam. 24.24. And how will you take up the Cross, Sir, and lay down your Life for <hi>Christ,</hi> if you will not be but at so much <hi>Trouble,</hi> as I am putting you upon, for his sake? Does he not well <hi>Deserve</hi> it from you? And is he not <hi>Able</hi> to Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence you? Or will he Forget your Zeal for his <hi>Glory,</hi> who leaves not unrewarded so much as a <hi>Cup of Cold Water given to his Disciple?</hi> And will you stick at a little Trouble for such a <hi>Lord,</hi> as stuck not at the greatest Sufferings for you? But where are the Formidable <hi>Buggs,</hi> at which you start back? Who or what are you afraid of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43562:11"/> in his cause; O how did the <hi>Primitive Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> despise all the Indignities and Cruelties Barbarous <hi>Tyrants</hi> could cast upon 'em, rather than <hi>Dishonor</hi> him that Call'd 'em! They would Dye <hi>bravely</hi> for him, rather than Live <hi>basely</hi> without him. God be thanked, Sir, we are not brought to that <hi>Dilemma,</hi> no body threatens us now with Death or Danger for our Obedience. But we have the Laws of God and Man both on our side: And instead of <hi>Persecution</hi> for our Religion, there are <hi>Penalties</hi> for Affronting 'its Blessed <hi>Author.</hi> And when some will be so Wicked, as to <hi>Incur</hi> the Punishment rather than not <hi>Dishonor</hi> the Lord; Will you be so <hi>Pusillanimous,</hi> as to let them carry all before 'em, and say you will not Meddle, to stir in the <hi>Nests</hi> of such <hi>Venemous</hi> Creatures, that have <hi>Stings</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Tongues; least they should shew themselves, <hi>Like</hi> themselves? And alas, What can they do? And why will you be Daunted with a <hi>Rout</hi> of Rebels, engag'd in a <hi>Scandalous</hi> Cause? why such <hi>Cringing</hi> to their Humor, for dread of their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasure? True Courage and Resolution, Sir, will <hi>Steel</hi> and Harden you against more <hi>Arduous</hi> Encounters than these. Where indeed the Worst is at <hi>First:</hi> And it will make the Hard things Easie, but to be <hi>Resolv'd</hi> upon 'em, and <hi>Used</hi> to 'em.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43562:11"/> When you have but made your self known for an <hi>Avenger</hi> of Heaven's Affronts, you will not then be so <hi>Dar'd</hi> and Tempted every where. Your Acquaintance and Company will then be more Modest and <hi>Mannerly:</hi> And (holding themselves in from the Guilt) save you the labour of Punishing. When they see that you will bring those to Submit for Wrath who will not do it for <hi>Conscience Sake.</hi> Whereas if they find you <hi>Easie,</hi> and Careless of Gods Glory They'll make as Bold as they List with you, yea and take a <hi>Pride</hi> to Trample your Justice and Authority.</p>
            <p>Indeed if you will not <hi>Brow beat,</hi> but Encourage the Conscientious witnesses, I cannot promise you, Sir, but you may hear your <hi>Gates</hi> the oftner knockt at; and find somewhat more to do, in Hearing what they have to say. But would God, Sir, you had no worse <hi>Guests,</hi> than such as put you upon the <hi>Best work</hi> you can do: And though they give you a little Trouble at present, lay in matter for your future Everlasting <hi>Comfort.</hi> That you may hear at the last from your great Master, <hi>Well done Good and Faithful servant Enter thou in to the Joy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly. Are you afraid of getting <hi>Ill-will,</hi> should you Pursue matters Home, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43562:12"/> to the Tenure of this good <hi>Law, against Cursing and Swearing?</hi> 'Tis very like, Sir, you may be Spighted, for your Zeal and <hi>Warmness</hi> upon such Occasions. We may well expect the Obnoxious to <hi>Bark,</hi> and make a Noise, and rather shew their Rage, than their Gladness, at the Remedy newly provided: And how much they had rather, that no such <hi>Rubs</hi> and <hi>Bars</hi> had been laid across the Swearers way. But are these, Sir, to be Judges in the Case? must the <hi>Malefactors</hi> get up on the Bench to Arraign the Laws that are against them? What if they call it nothing but <hi>Ill-will</hi> and Malice, which you know to be the truest Friendship and Kindness? You must not be so much Concerned, Sir, to <hi>Please,</hi> as to <hi>Save</hi> them: Nor think it worth while to Gratifie their Humour, or Court their Favour, at the Loss of his Honor and Love, to whom you are infinitely more <hi>Oblig'd,</hi> and who is infinitely more to be <hi>Regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> (not only than the contemptible <hi>Rabble,</hi> but) than the dearest <hi>Friends,</hi> or the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest <hi>Potentates.</hi> What if <hi>Men</hi> do not Like you, when <hi>God</hi> with his Favour Embraces you? Will you value the Approbation of pitiful <hi>Worms,</hi> above his Countenance, who is the <hi>Greatest</hi> and the <hi>Best?</hi> What if they be Angry, on whom you Inflict the Penalty? When <hi>'tis Anger without a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43562:12"/> Cause,</hi> being nothing at all but what they have pull'd on their own heads? And what is the Loss of a Little <hi>Money,</hi> to prevent the Loss of a <hi>Soul,</hi> more Worth than the whole World? Such as are Souer with you, Sir, when you do them but Justice and Kindness, will after find you a better Friend, than any of their own <hi>Knot,</hi> that Swear how they Love 'em, and Swear at you, for Abusing 'em. Tis nothing but their <hi>Distemper</hi> that makes them now so <hi>Frantick:</hi> If ever they come to be Healed, they will be otherwise minded. And who would regard the Exclamations of a <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Rout against him? Or to <hi>Lose</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with such as are Lost to all that is <hi>Wise</hi> and <hi>Good?</hi> If these Stomach you, for doing them Justice, and God Glory, Does it sway so much with you, Sir, what such as they say, who care not what the <hi>Lord</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Says? What matter for the Opinion or the <hi>Prate</hi> of those, that are so extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out? O, Sir, Scorn the Noise of such Enemies to God, as the <hi>Common Swearers:</hi> Who will all be struck <hi>Speechless</hi> in the Judgment, and made to eat their Words, and the <hi>Tongues</hi> too, which they us'd as Weapons of Rebellion against Heaven.</p>
            <p>But are you startled to find some of better <hi>Note</hi> and Worth among 'em? If so,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43562:13"/> Sir, you'll be very Kind to these, in shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and scaring them out of such <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> Company. Are they Good <hi>Honest</hi> Men? <hi>Wise</hi> Men? And Persons of <hi>Honor</hi> too? And of these you are most Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to incur the Displeasure. And here you think you had best <hi>Consider</hi> well what you do. And I will now take it into Consideration, with you.</p>
            <p>Do you then hear the <hi>Good Honest</hi> man Guilty of <hi>Prophane Cursing and Swearing?</hi> If that be Possible; It's great Pity: and should such be the Case, you'll do well to Commend the man for his <hi>Honesty:</hi> but not stick to Punish him for his <hi>Impiety.</hi> Peradventure he is so far Honest, as not to be a <hi>Lier,</hi> a <hi>Theif,</hi> or <hi>Adulterer?</hi> Tho you know, Sir, that the Notion which some have of their Good <hi>Honest</hi> man, will take in a very <hi>Lewd</hi> man, and one that is far from being an <hi>Upright, Just</hi> man. For an Honest man, we say, will be as <hi>Good as his Word.</hi> And even common Justice will oblige him to Render unto all their <hi>Dues.</hi> But how is he as Good as his <hi>Word,</hi> who makes nothing of the most Solemn Engagement to his <hi>God?</hi> And what Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring to all their <hi>Dues?</hi> When God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self is by such, left out of the <hi>Reckoning,</hi> and no Care taken to pay unto him whom
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43562:13"/> they owe most of all to, the <hi>Honour due to his Name?</hi> and what Trust is to be reposed in his Honesty, who can be so <hi>False</hi> to God and to his own Soul? Surely, Sir, that mans <hi>Goodness</hi> must lye in a very Narrow Compass, who can be found in such a <hi>Horrid</hi> Guilt against the Honor of God, and against his strictest Commands, and his most Terrible Threatnings, as the <hi>Common Swearing;</hi> which gives Evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a man, that he is <hi>(laesae Majestatis reus)</hi> Guilty of <hi>High Treason</hi> against the Crown and Dignity of Heaven. A Wickedness which stands in so direct Opposition to our <hi>Christian Rule,</hi> that I see not how any man can be indeed a <hi>Christian</hi> who allows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in it. And I know not where is his Conscience or Integrity, who dare com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Blaspheme the <hi>Blessed Name,</hi> that ought for ever to be had in the highest <hi>Veneration,</hi> and never to be mentioned, but with all Religious Reverence and Awful Regard. I doubt not, Sir, but you have heard many a <hi>Notorious</hi> Swearer called a Good <hi>Honest</hi> Fellow; But I hope such his <hi>Reputed</hi> Goodness shall not Terrifie you from doing him <hi>Justice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again Do you think, Sir, you must not take upon you to Correct the man of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, and the <hi>Scholar,</hi> who should
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43562:14"/> know what they have to do, and not need to be so <hi>Tutor'd?</hi> But if such have yet learn'd no better manners, than to be <hi>common Swearers,</hi> Be sure that is none of their <hi>Wisdom.</hi> And when they will so play the <hi>Fool,</hi> I think they ought never the less, but so much the more to <hi>Smart</hi> for it, because they know more than the <hi>Most,</hi> and yet do as bad as the <hi>Worst.</hi> Alas, Sir, how does the <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible</hi> Mans Wisdom here most wretchedly fail him, To think that God does not <hi>Hear,</hi> or will not <hi>Require</hi> it, or could not <hi>Avenge</hi> it? And to venture Purse and Soul, for no Purchase, but his own, and Gods Disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor? Wise men use to make better <hi>Bargains,</hi> than to pay a dear Rate, for that which is stark naught. 'Tis the <hi>Fool</hi> that parts with his Money so Easily. And will you Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence the Wisdom of that <hi>Absurd</hi> Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who can find a God to <hi>Swear</hi> by, but none to <hi>Pray</hi> to? That piece of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, who owns a Glorious God, only to <hi>Disrobe,</hi> and Plunder him of his Glory? Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the God-Provoking and Soul Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wickedness, like <hi>Horse and Mule that have no Understanding.</hi> Because the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderate wretches are Blinded and Lost in their own Follies and Impieties, they think the <hi>Omniscient God</hi> must see and know no more than such <hi>Bruits</hi> as themselves: And shew what a Vile Opinion they have of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43562:14"/> God's <hi>Inspection,</hi> When they can be more Dasht and aw'd with the Presence of a poor <hi>Mortal</hi> Man, Than with the Observation of the only Wise Eternal <hi>God.</hi> Well does the <hi>Psalmist</hi> lash such Beasts of the people, Psalm. 94.8, 9, 10. <hi>Understand ye Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish among the people, and ye Fools when will ye be Wise! He that planted the Ear, shall he not Hear? He that formed the Eye, shall he not See? He that Teacheth man Knowledg shall not he know?</hi> How Judicious and Cunning soever they may be accounted, would any Wise men, at the <hi>Peril</hi> of their Immortal Souls, make so Bold with the great <hi>God,</hi> Holy and Just, and think he will always so take it at their hands? Would they so des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately Throw at him, as if they could easily deal with him? Do they know whom they <hi>Resist?</hi> When better have the whole World, and all men and <hi>Devils,</hi> than one <hi>God</hi> against them. O what an Unequal <hi>Match</hi> is it, Sir, for a pitiful crawling Worm, to oppose the <hi>Invincible</hi> Power that Rear'd and Sustains all the mighty Fabrick of Heaven and Earth? who but a <hi>Mad-Man</hi> will be for the Desperate Service, to Fight with a <hi>Consuming Fire?</hi> Silly Animals! How soon can he <hi>Kill, and Cast thee into Hell?</hi> Let the <hi>Postheard</hi> Strive with the <hi>Postheards</hi> of the Earth: Wo to that <hi>Fool-hardy</hi> Sinner, who will enter the <hi>Lists,</hi> to try Strength
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43562:15"/> with his <hi>Omnipotent Maker! The Foolish people have Blasphemed thy Name.</hi> Psal. 74.18. None else would ever offer to do it. And surely, Sir, as well may you venture to Confront their <hi>Wisdom,</hi> as they to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front the <hi>Wisdom of the Nation,</hi> in Playing with that as but a <hi>Jesting Matter,</hi> which our great <hi>Senate</hi> calls a <hi>Detestable Sin:</hi> And thinks fit to shew their Horror of it, in making the Strictest Law against it. Is it so Heinous to call them to account, who can be so senseless to <hi>Exasperate</hi> the Lord and for ever to Lose God? By taking the Impudent Liberty, ever and anon to offer him such <hi>Barbarous</hi> Indignities? What if they take it ill to be <hi>Controuled,</hi> who, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Sence,</hi> and against all the Fear of God (and is it were, in Spight of him) take and keep up such a wickedness; which one would imagine should need no more, but any considering man's <hi>Bethinking</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, to turn his heart against it, and make him Resolve, never to have any thing more to do with it?</p>
            <p>But is any <hi>Great man,</hi> or Person of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> in this foul Guilt? And must they be made Exceptions from the Common Rules of Justice? And do you think, Sir, it would be accounted an Offence greater than all their <hi>Swearing,</hi> and never to be <hi>Forgiven,</hi> should you let the Law have its Course there,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43562:15"/> and put their <hi>Honors,</hi> or their <hi>Worships upon Record?</hi> But are not they the Kings <hi>Subjects</hi> as well as others? And is there ever a Clause in the Act to Exempt the <hi>Noble</hi> or <hi>Gentile</hi> Swearers? Must that Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility <hi>Indemnifie,</hi> which renders them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but the more <hi>deeply</hi> Guilty? Because they move in a <hi>Sphear</hi> above others, and are more observed and followed; and so capable of doing the greater good or Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, Their <hi>Exorbitant</hi> Pattern and Poyso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Influence therefore makes them more <hi>Responsible,</hi> for all whom they Seduce and Ruine. And if Noble Men will <hi>Prophanely Curse and Swear,</hi> Sure they are never the <hi>Nobler</hi> for it: Tho they may think so to add to their <hi>Grandure,</hi> and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves look <hi>Bigger</hi> still, by such <hi>Thundring</hi> against Heaven, and shewing how Bold they dare make with him, whom all the World <hi>Adores:</hi> Swearing for the <hi>Gallantry</hi> of the thing, to be thought the Braver men, for venturing so to set the Great God at <hi>Defiance.</hi> Is this their Ingenuity and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, so to <hi>Depress</hi> him that has <hi>Exalted</hi> them? And when they are Rais'd to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, To have a <hi>Pique</hi> at his Honor, Least it should Darken them, to own a <hi>Greater</hi> than themselves; Does it not rather, Sir, extreamly Lessen their <hi>Character,</hi> so to Scorn their Glorious <hi>Maker,</hi> and greatest
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43562:16"/>
               <hi>Benefactor?</hi> O what Loses a man more, than the very <hi>Pride</hi> and Haughtiness, whereby he reckons only still more to <hi>Greaten</hi> himself? And of all the Proud Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, which so Detestable as the <hi>Insolence</hi> against God, and Scorning to be under him? What Honor can I have for him, who has none for his <hi>God?</hi> Indeed how can he ever expect it from me? When men of outward Dignity will so <hi>Degrade</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, by their Impiety; How can we help it that they make themselves <hi>Vile,</hi> and fit only to be Despised, by all whose eyes God hath opened? <hi>Psal.</hi> 15 4. If they will be found some of the Cursed Crew, that are the <hi>Hate</hi> of Heaven, who that is true to the Honor of his Lord, can heartily Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor such Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ts of his <hi>Contempt?</hi> who do but teach others to <hi>Slight</hi> them, As they do One that is infinitely more their <hi>Superior?</hi> What Names or <hi>Titles</hi> can Credit that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godliness, which makes them Enemies to God? If they will fall so <hi>stout</hi> upon Him; after he has so highly Obliged them, Is it not the more <hi>shame</hi> for 'em? For certainly God will make his <hi>Despisers Despised.</hi> In good truth they do make themselves so. And they must not think to have the Less Contempt, but the Greater, because they are such <hi>Great</hi> Enemies. Tho we must not be so <hi>Rude</hi> to deny them the Civil Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43562:16"/> due to their Places, yet neither must we be so <hi>Impious,</hi> to Honor them, to Gods Dishonor. And what reason have we to Respect them more, than they do the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Lord</hi> that made them? How can I fall down to them, as the <hi>Sons of Honor,</hi> who can take a Pride to turn their Tongues to his <hi>Reproach,</hi> without whom they could not so much as <hi>Move</hi> them at all? And like some surly Animals, lye <hi>Snapping</hi> at the Hand that gives them <hi>Bread?</hi> shall Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to Heaven think to be <hi>Honorable,</hi> for that which makes them <hi>Abominable?</hi> If they will throw themselves upon a Level with the <hi>Rascally</hi> people, for that sort of Wickedness which even the Basest <hi>Villain</hi> has as good a Claim to, and can make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self as Eminent for. They must not take it Heinously to be served accordingly. Or take it as they will, 'Tis the most <hi>Unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> thing for any, that have a Sense of Gods Honor, to pay a Profound Honor to his Notorious Enemies. If the Best and Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test in the World must never be Preferred before <hi>Him:</hi> Much less must we Slight him for the sake of some of the most <hi>Corrupt</hi> Limbs of Mankind, who would be Famous for their <hi>Daring</hi> Impieties, and be thought Great for Exalting themselves above all the Commands and Threats of God: Scorning to be so <hi>Low-Spirited,</hi> as to Fear
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43562:17"/> Hell and Damnation; and Flowting them that hearken so much to the Despis'd <hi>Jesus,</hi> whom it seems themselves Bow to, only in <hi>Mockery:</hi> And when our great Law-Giver bids them, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> they in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, reply Pish we Regard it not at all. Let him say what he will, we will be <hi>Above</hi> his Word. But they shall not be Above his <hi>Judgments.</hi> Nor are they above the <hi>Laws</hi> neither, were they but duely Executed.</p>
            <p>You see, Sir, in the late <hi>Posthumous</hi> Print, What a Person of <hi>Honor</hi> has said, to the everlasting Dishonor of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stomary Swearing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Boyle.</hi>
               </note> In shewing how Silly and <hi>Defenseless</hi> is the Wickedness; and taking so much pains to <hi>Expose</hi> it: that he might A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gue, and School, and shame those of his <hi>Quality,</hi> out of that <hi>Rudeness</hi> with Heaven, which casts such a <hi>Blot</hi> on their Nobility, that he counts it <hi>Impudent</hi> in them to expect our Esteem, and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuseness</hi> in us, to Squander it upon them, for the Recompence of their <hi>Vice.</hi> And I hope, Sir, you will think that Renowned <hi>Author</hi> fitter to be Heard than any the Proudest <hi>Swearer.</hi> The World knows he had sense and <hi>Honor</hi> all over. But all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Swearers make themselves Senseless and <hi>Ignominious,</hi> And so they are to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded thereafter.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43562:17"/>
            <p>Be they who or what they will then, Sir, that put themselves under the <hi>Devil</hi>'s Banner, to engage in that Cursed Cause, they are not too <hi>Wise,</hi> nor too <hi>Good,</hi> nor too <hi>Great,</hi> to Answer for it to <hi>God</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; nor to the <hi>Powers Ordained of God</hi> in this World. And therefore, Fear not, Sir, to shew your self for the God of Heaven, tho it be against a whole <hi>Host</hi> of the Proudest of his Foes, who must and shall be all confounded and <hi>Quell'd.</hi> And though you should thus be out with them, The Wisest and Best of men will <hi>Like</hi> you never the worse for that. But you shall have the sweet Satisfaction from <hi>Within,</hi> and that Blessed Peace from <hi>Above,</hi> as will more than make you Amends for all their Flouts and Frowns.</p>
            <p>Sixthly. Are you afraid, Sir, to be Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured for <hi>Singular, Precise,</hi> and <hi>a Busie-Body;</hi> should you faithfully Acquit your self in your Place as a truly Christian <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate;</hi> To Countenance the Pious and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the Prophane? Do you ask me, What, shall I be like <hi>No body,</hi> to go and set my self vigorously against the <hi>Common Swearers?</hi> I am heartily sorry, Sir, if the Age be so Degenerate that you should just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doubt of <hi>Company</hi> in so Laudable an <hi>Enterprise.</hi> Yet I hope you will not stand
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43562:18"/> alone; but find a happy <hi>Concurrence</hi> of such as shall equally Concern themselves in the Trust committed to you I am <hi>Sure</hi> of some, and <hi>Hopeful</hi> of many more, that will be with you.</p>
            <p>But should never so many stand off; what Hazard would it be to your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that you are not like the <hi>Most,</hi> and that you keep in a <hi>Narower</hi> Path than is commonly taken? If your Example must be the <hi>Reproof</hi> of others, the Shame will be theirs, but the greater Honour still to your self; That you do the thing, which they ought to do, and are greatly to <hi>Blame,</hi> to Hide themselves in the most Glorious Case. Tis Grating, I know, Sir, That your Zeal should pluck some of your Brethren by the <hi>Sleeve;</hi> but must you, in such a grand <hi>Complement</hi> to them, bear them Company in the Notorious Neglect of their Duty? And not offer to be Faithful to your Trust, because so Few will be your Partners in the Work? Can you think it Best to do as the Most do? When he that Made you, and will Judge you, Forbids you to <hi>Follow the Multitude,</hi> if it be <hi>to do Evil?</hi> Whatever be their Names or Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as they can none of 'em, by their Examples, <hi>Extenuate,</hi> or alter the Nature of Guilt, to make the <hi>Detestable</hi> Sin, a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43562:18"/> Peccadillo; So neither can they Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or <hi>Alleviate</hi> the Punishment of their Followers, who on the Presumption of their Judgment or Practice, will Venture to be their <hi>Companions</hi> in the common Corruptions, and Palliations of 'em.</p>
            <p>Sociable Sinners, that followed the <hi>Multitude</hi> in their Lewd Courses, must look to share with them in their Just Curses. And to be found Upright in the midst of a Crocked and Perverse Generation, is no small Commendation, and will find more than a Common Salvation. But how can you, Sir, be trusty to your <hi>Lord,</hi> when Determined more by others ways, than by his <hi>Word?</hi> And what Life of Grace do you shew, when you Swim as <hi>Dead</hi> things do, only down the Common <hi>Stream?</hi> O let your Zealous Concern, like a mighty <hi>Torrent,</hi> shew but the greater Fierceness for Opposition. And let others <hi>Perfidious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> have no other Influence upon you, but only to provoke you in a holy <hi>Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at them, to go beyond them.</p>
            <p>But if you think it such Ill manners, Sir, not to Comply with the Rest, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so much out, or Shamefully <hi>Deficient:</hi> Then where is the Good Manners to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43562:19"/> and now to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> the highest Powers we have on Earth, when they shall all be Slighted, in Complyance with a Sorry <hi>Pack,</hi> and a very Criminal Party? If you look about you for company, Sir, to see who will be on your side, before you Stir: If you ask, as Psal. 94.16 <hi>Who will Rise up for me against the Evil doers? Or who will Stand up for me against the Workers of Iniquity?</hi> God be thanked, Sir, No such room now for the Objection of that <hi>Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity,</hi> When you have the <hi>King</hi> himself, to whose Example all use to be so Proud of Shaping themselves, and one of the most <hi>August</hi> Assemblies in the World, to be your <hi>Abettors,</hi> in standing up to Fight the <hi>Lords</hi> Battels.</p>
            <p>Or should you, by some still, be thought never so Singular, yet I see no Cause you have to be Asham'd of it <hi>Singularly,</hi> which the Wisdom of <hi>God,</hi> and the Wisdom of the <hi>Nation</hi> puts you upon. And though you had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so much Company as you have, yet how much better, Sir, to be Pious <hi>alone,</hi> than Ungodly, with never so much <hi>Company?</hi> I know you will, one day, be glad to be found among the <hi>Little Flock;</hi> and I understand not why you should count it so <hi>Infamous,</hi> though you be one of 'em at present.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:43562:19"/>
            <p>And as little Startling (if you well Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider it, Sir) is the Charge of <hi>Preciseness.</hi> For you cannot but know what sort of men use to call that <hi>Holiness,</hi> without which no man shall see the Lord, by this Name. And there are Terms of <hi>Reputed</hi> Infamy, that much more <hi>Credit,</hi> than <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace</hi> the persons they are cast at: If we but observe what kind of <hi>Nomenclators</hi> they come from: such as Brand every thing with a hard <hi>Title,</hi> that does not jump with their own debauch'd and Prophane humor. And you shall quickly have never a Vertue, Grace, or Good Quality left you, Sir, if you must be run out of it, as fast as any Silly Tongues or Black mouths <hi>Mis-call</hi> it. <hi>If they have called the Master of the house Belzebub, how much more shall they call them of his houshold?</hi> Mat. 10.25. And if you are Derided on this account, It will be with abundance of the <hi>Best Company:</hi> When not only all Conscientious <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Ministers,</hi> but <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> also are now some of these <hi>Precisi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns.</hi> You are a Young Christian if you cannot Slight and <hi>Scorn</hi> the Slanders of such <hi>Authors:</hi> For Displeasing whom, any cause is indeed but so much the Better to be <hi>Lik'd.</hi> But you know, Sir, who charges you to <hi>Walk Circumspectly,</hi> be they never so many of your Acquaintance, who are for walking
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43562:20"/> at Large, after the <hi>Course of this World,</hi> And you know <hi>What manner of persons we ought to be in all holy Conversation and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness:</hi> And when alas, so <hi>Few</hi> are really such, The Word which you profess to Believe for Eternal Truth, will tell you, How few are like to be <hi>for ever Happy.</hi> And God grant, Sir, That you and I may be of that <hi>Number,</hi> however they hear now from a Vain Mistaken World.</p>
            <p>But you would not be thought a <hi>Busy-Body?</hi> Nor would I ever perswade you, Sir, to be such, in the Infamous sense which holy <hi>Scripture</hi> condemns. For, as <hi>Impertinents</hi> can be busie, without Working at all, and take a deal of Pains to do <hi>Nothing</hi> (All their <hi>Fermentation</hi> being but a mere <hi>Nugation,</hi> and the eager pursuit of that which turns to no Account) So 'tis a Fault that Creates abundance of Mischief in the World, when we will be such <hi>Eccentricks,</hi> to concern our selves in others Affairs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any good <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all,</hi> and to no good <hi>End:</hi> More for Curiosity, or Malignity, than for any necessity or charity. And there may be the great <hi>Outcry</hi> against others vices, but to <hi>Hide</hi> our own: And a heavy <hi>Crimination</hi> of them, only to <hi>Set off</hi> our selves. But ill does the Office sit upon any one, to be such a <hi>Keeper of the Vineyards,</hi> as to let all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43562:20"/> lie <hi>Uncultivated</hi> at Home. When he is to <hi>Begin</hi> there, and to be Severest upon <hi>Himself,</hi> where he may make Boldest. Nor must our Zeal out run either our Discretion, or our Meekness, or our tender Consideration of others Infirmities, and our Charitable Allowance for their Unavoidable Failings. But when Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting our <hi>Brother overtaken with a Fault we must consider our selves, lest we also be Tempted.</hi> And not be so <hi>Byassed</hi> with any Piques or Partialities, but that we Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously proceed by <hi>Regular</hi> steps, in the <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightness</hi> of our hearts; and carefully keep within the Compass both of Gods Laws and Mans.</p>
            <p>Yet this notwithstanding, Sir, There is a <hi>Looking also on the things of others,</hi> which is a Commanded Duty. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.4. And the best of the <hi>Seven</hi> Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. was Praised for this, That she <hi>could not Bear them that were Evil.</hi> And though some expect much Commendation for their quiet <hi>peaceable</hi> humor, when they cry, Let every one look to themselves, <hi>We will not Meddle nor make:</hi> yet you know, Sir, How good a man he was that doggedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Am I my Brothers Keeper?</hi> Gen. 4.9. And indeed such as have turn'd up the <hi>Reins,</hi> and forgot the Government of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43562:21"/> are like to be no well-willers to any good <hi>Discipline,</hi> but had rather all should be left at <hi>Random,</hi> than any Restraint laid upon such as need it, to <hi>Oblige</hi> them to be better than they have a Mind to. Such as most put forth themselves for the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, and the Good of our <hi>Souls,</hi> these are the <hi>Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> Medlers, which of any, they can least away with; As most Disturbing their beloved <hi>Security;</hi> and Labouring to Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce that <hi>Reverence</hi> of God, and <hi>Regularity</hi> of Life, which sevres only to <hi>Exasperate</hi> them, and put 'em to Confusion.</p>
            <p>But the Charity, Sir, which teaches you to <hi>Love your Neighbour as your Self,</hi> can do no less sure, than oblige you to be Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Preventing his <hi>Hurt,</hi> and Promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Good,</hi> by all means under your <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> whenever it falls in your way. And if every Christian in his capacity, what in him lies, stand engag'd to care for the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Good, and for his <hi>Neighbours</hi> Good, Much more the <hi>Magistrate</hi> and the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi> And who then but the Silly or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse, will call them <hi>Busy Bodies,</hi> for the Faithful and Zealous Discharge of their <hi>Offices?</hi> which cheifly consist in the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Regulation of others? But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>Censors</hi> are hard upon 'em for it, they ought to be so Busie, and <hi>Hoc Agere:</hi> That
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43562:21"/> they may not teach the people to <hi>Transgress,</hi> nor leave them to Stray and be Lost as sheep without <hi>Sheppards:</hi> But watch over 'em, and be <hi>Intent</hi> upon this very thing, as those that must be Accountable for all that Perish, through their Neglect and Default. And such as are now Traduced, for doing more than <hi>Others,</hi> will not think they have <hi>Over-done</hi> it, when they come to dye: But the Lazy and Perfidious Magistrates and Ministers, that are only Busie in <hi>Censuring</hi> such as Exceed them, shall then too late wish, they had done Like 'em.</p>
            <p>Be pleas'd then, Sir, to accept in good part that Word of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> wherein I shall also think my Self concern'd to take a Share. Seeing now a <hi>Price</hi> is put into all our hands, and every one is impower'd if not by admonition or correction to reclaim others, yet by Testimony, to bring the Offenders that Plague us to <hi>Punishment:</hi> O that it may Awaken all our Zeal, to Suppress and Grub up the Rampant, <hi>Topping</hi> Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, that so long has Reign'd and Swag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, to set all the former Laws at Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. However the Children of the <hi>Devil,</hi> his Trusty Servants, swell and hang their heads at the Attempt, to Dispossess their <hi>Master.</hi> Sure all that Fear and Love God will Rejoyce in the <hi>New</hi> Opportunity now set before us. And in the name of God, Sir,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43562:22"/> let us take Heart, and make some fresh <hi>Experiments,</hi> to see what will be done now, more than yet has been done; to Deliver us from this <hi>Curse</hi> and <hi>Reproach,</hi> that has so long lain upon us. And let not such an Excellent Statute lie as a <hi>Dead</hi> thing among us; Lest it one day <hi>Rise</hi> up in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against us. Let us neither be Asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nor Afraid to do the Justice, whereby those. Ends may be obtained, that are now Designed. Instead of Pleasing the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal <hi>Faction</hi> into their Ruin, and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them quite to <hi>Undoe</hi> the Land which so long they have made to <hi>Groan</hi> under 'em: Rather be pleased, Sir, to Imitate our Wise and Pious <hi>Law-Makers,</hi> who from the common Corruption, and even Universal <hi>Prevalence</hi> of this Crying Wickedness, have taken occasion to express their Keener <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentments</hi> against it; Contriving the Good <hi>Law,</hi> which Blessed be God that put it into the hearts of some to Promote, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered 'em in the wishes of their hearts, to see it brought to perfection. And O that none of those who should <hi>Awe</hi> the Prophane Generation, and make them Afraid to be so Rude with Heaven in their Presence, may give 'em <hi>Boldness</hi> yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to carry on the wicked Humor: But, if it be Possible, help to Stop them in the ill <hi>Damnable</hi> way they are upon, and make others dread to follow 'em.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:43562:22"/>
            <p>But before I press you, Sir, with the <hi>Enforcements</hi> of this Exhortation, let me here give you the Apostles Caution, Jud. 22. <hi>Of some have Compassion, Making a Difference.</hi> For even of Swearers that are Faulty, all are not alike Guilty; And some therefore to be used with <hi>Lenity,</hi> Others to be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led more <hi>Severely.</hi> They be <hi>Prophane Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> whom the <hi>Act</hi> has mark'd out for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution: and though all Swearing is <hi>Prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hane,</hi> that is not <hi>Sacred:</hi> And none is Sacred, but what is made an Act of <hi>Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship;</hi> Solemnly to Invocate the Searcher of Hearts, and the Judge of Right and Wrong, as the <hi>Witness</hi> of our Truth, and Sincerity, and the <hi>Avenger</hi> of all Falshood and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: which we are never to do, but upon very Weighty occasions, and when we have a Just Call to it, and good Warrant for it. Yet by <hi>Prophane,</hi> I humbly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the <hi>Act</hi> intends all such Bold and Rude Swearing, in common chat, as is <hi>Inconsistent</hi> with the Fear of God, and so highly <hi>Offensive</hi> to all Sober Good men. For even the man whose heart, in the main, is <hi>Right with God,</hi> may yet Transgress through <hi>Inadvertence,</hi> and Surprize, and the Violence and urgency of <hi>Temptations:</hi> And as soon, as he is made sensible of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43562:23"/>
               <hi>Slip,</hi> declare his Concernment with Sorrow for it, and severely Judge himself, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thank his Monitor, and seriously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise Amendment. And in my opinion, Sir, such a case calls for <hi>Pity,</hi> rather than the <hi>Penalty.</hi> Surely, Sir, a great Distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to be made between this, and the Mad <hi>Customary-Swearer?</hi> That Swears on, as in <hi>Defiance</hi> of Laws Human and Divine; and Extenuates, if not Justifies the Guilt, makes a Mock of his Sin, and Advocates for it: And instead of Recoiling upon himself, is ready rather to fly in the face of his Reprover: Scorns all Warning, will not be Reclaimed, is far from being Asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and <hi>Hates to be Reformed.</hi> What is the Law designed for, Sir, if not to <hi>Maul</hi> and Batter, or at least to <hi>Muzzel</hi> and Chain up such Head-Strong <hi>Beasts</hi> of the People; that make even a <hi>Trade</hi> of Swearing, as if they had been Bound to the <hi>Devil,</hi> and serv'd their <hi>Apprentiship;</hi> and become such Masters of the Hellish <hi>Craft,</hi> that they are past all Apprehensions of the <hi>Horror,</hi> and scarce so much as take notice, even of the thing it self: And instead of Fearing an Oath, count nothing more Ridiculous, than such <hi>Preciseness:</hi> Swearing so thick, as if they were in Hast, to <hi>fill up the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of their Wickedness,</hi> and would take the <hi>Shortest Cut</hi> to that Damnation which they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43562:23"/> so often <hi>Imprecate.</hi> When they scarce use the Name of <hi>God,</hi> but as their <hi>Bauble,</hi> and make him the matter of their Infernal <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment;</hi> Where the Children of Hell Smile, and shew how much they are taken with the Humour; to see their Maker and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Run down and Trampled: As if the gread <hi>Lord</hi> of all were not so good as their <hi>Servant;</hi> And he whom they fall on their Knees to in the <hi>Church,</hi> were fit only to be <hi>Ridicul'd</hi> somewhere else. Even in such Fraternities, whose <hi>Dearness</hi> arises only from the Humour of <hi>Prophaneness;</hi> and they are great <hi>Friends,</hi> for being all of 'em Gods <hi>Enemies:</hi> such Enemies as can never let him alone, but Pursue him even Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. And as our Enemy is for hitting us in the place where he thinks we can least Endure to be <hi>Touch'd,</hi> and we are too Free in pouring out words to the Disgrace of those whom we do not <hi>Love,</hi> so if God be most Tender of his <hi>Glory,</hi> they are most madly bent against it: If their Impious Swearing so Highly <hi>Affront</hi> him, he shall be sure to have <hi>Enough</hi> of it; and nothing more usually heard amongst them. As if they would even pluck the <hi>Crown</hi> off his head, and strike into the very <hi>Apple of his Eye.</hi> O what a Sting and Rancor does it argue at the bottom, when from the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance</hi> of the Heart the Mouth so pours
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43562:24"/> out! Such monstrous <hi>Excrescencies</hi> and filthy Botches of their common Discourse, noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously betray the Malignant Putrid <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> whence they Proceed. But I need not add any thing to <hi>Blacken</hi> their Names, who are so hard at it, to <hi>Foam out their own Shame.</hi> But truly, Sir, such <hi>Captains</hi> in the Devils Troops, the <hi>Jeroboams that make others Sin,</hi> they need the <hi>Lash</hi> which the Law has provided. And I must tell you Sir, 'Tis very dangerous to be any <hi>Abettors</hi> of 'em, or to have any part or Lot with the Rebels, at whose Destruction God will <hi>Laugh,</hi> as they do at his <hi>Dishonor.</hi> Even to Excuse for them, may be <hi>Innuendo,</hi> suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make you reckoned as one of 'em. And such as make Light of the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, do but make themselves too well known for greater Friends to Gods Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, than to Himself: And more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to take their Part than to Appear and Contend for his Honor.</p>
            <p>Ah, Dear Sir, who that has any thing of God's Grace in his heart can sit still, and Tamely hear <hi>Peals</hi> of Oaths Rung in his ears, and the Almighty Lord of all Dar'd and Vilified, by every Wretched Swearer? O here if ever, Sir, shew your <hi>Zeal for the Lord of Hosts.</hi> Let your Spirit be <hi>Stirred,</hi> and your Heart <hi>Burn</hi> within you, to hear
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43562:24"/> the Horrid Oaths and Curses, whereby the great name of God is so Dishonored, and our Religion made a Very Scorn to <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Infidel</hi> World. Especially Look narrowly to all within your particular <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strict;</hi> as many as ever you can Influence, that what so highly Provokes God may never Thrive under your <hi>Shadow.</hi> For this is the <hi>Filial</hi> Ingenious Love of God, more greviously to Resent the Dishonor done to our Heavenly Father, than any Disgrace reflected on our selves: And to count his Foes more Noisom to us, than any that touch us so in our own Dearest Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests: yea to Pursue them as our worst Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, tho not to Reak our <hi>Vengeance,</hi> yet in Legal ways, to help them to <hi>Justice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your own Wrongs, Sir, it will become you to Personate the <hi>Deaf</hi> man: But so to put up the Indignities against the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of Heaven were such <hi>Misprision</hi> of Treason, as would render your self <hi>Obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> And if at one time you can <hi>Diessmble</hi> your Observation of that, which you <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> at another, telling how many Oaths you heard such a one swear: what do you but thus bear <hi>Witness</hi> against your self, what a Subject you are to God and the King both; And how many <hi>Forfeitures</hi> you should have taken, which you did not; And so how
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43562:25"/> many bigger <hi>Amercements</hi> ought to be Levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you for that Default? When such Injury and Affront is offer'd to the best Laws, That in cases so Notorious, <hi>Justice</hi> should no better be done, even by those that are set up on purpose to do it.</p>
            <p>Whoever beg your <hi>Pardon</hi> here, Sir, 'tis not in your Power to <hi>Forgive</hi> 'em. All that I understand you can Lawfully do, is as an Equitable Judge, to Temper your <hi>Summum Jus,</hi> and Abate the Rigor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Quality of the Offender: <hi>i. e.</hi> If he be not Impudent and Hardned, But Relenting and Hopeful. But to let the <hi>Laughing</hi> and the <hi>Resolute</hi> Swearer Escape, is not Mercy, but Treachery yea and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: Cruelty to his Soul, and to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, both which he is Labouring to Ruine.</p>
            <p>In a common Calamity, Sir, As when a Town is on <hi>Fire,</hi> every Neighbour is to Lend a Helping hand, all to do what they can. And if there be no Saving the Whole, yet to Rescue as much as they are able out of the devouring Flames. And when our <hi>Nation</hi> is under such a Calamity, by reason of the Common Wickedness, this in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular of <hi>Customary Swearing,</hi> so Flagrant and Raging every where, the Tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such a <hi>Fire as enflames the very Course of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43562:25"/> Nature, and is it self set on Fire of Hell. Jam.</hi> 3.6. shall we stand by as Unconcerned <hi>Spectators,</hi> and instead of offering any Help, shew our selves much pleased with the Sight? Like <hi>Nero</hi> who Fiddled, and made himself merry with the Fire that burnt down his <hi>City.</hi> (A Pleasure fit for one of such a <hi>Stigmatized</hi> Name as all do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor!) O no Sir, God forbid, we should be so wretchedly Stupid, so obdurately Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But as in a dreadful Fire, the doleful Cry is, <hi>Help, O Help for the Lords sake:</hi> so here, let Magistrates and Ministers and all private Christians, in their respective Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Help, Help for the Lords sake.</hi> And for our dear <hi>Church</hi> and Countrey's sake; Yea for <hi>Credit,</hi> and <hi>Conscience</hi> sakes; and for all our precious <hi>Souls</hi> sake: That we may not bring them, nor our Land in <hi>Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy</hi> any more, either by falling into the Heinous guilt our selves; Or by our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance,</hi> or Indulgence, make our selves Accessary to the guilt of others.</p>
            <p>First then, Good Sir, <hi>Help for God</hi>'s <hi>sake:</hi> and do somewhat like the Obliged of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for him that <hi>Made</hi> you, and has been so abundantly <hi>Kind</hi> to you. Will you Espouse the Quarrel of your <hi>Friend</hi> and in a Generous Indignation, shew your Warmth and Mettle, at his Defamation,
<q>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:43562:26"/>
                  <l>If any touch my Friend or his Good Name,</l>
                  <l>It is my Honor and my Love, to Free</l>
                  <l>His Blasted Fame</l>
                  <l>From the least Spot, or thought of Blame.</l>
               </q> And does not your Supreme <hi>Benefactor</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve as well from you? When one in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is infinitely more your <hi>Friend</hi> than all your Friends upon Earth, Can you be, not only so Cold, but so Perfidious to him, when he is most coursely used; yea and most basely Affronted, not to think your self <hi>Concerned?</hi> O Sir, I hope you will not so Imitate those whom you ought to <hi>Punish,</hi> the <hi>Swearers</hi> that can stand upon the nicest <hi>Punctilios</hi> for themselves, but leave Gods Honor to shift for it self. Can you hang the head at a Reproachful word spoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst you, and <hi>Boyl</hi> with secret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, where the Enemy is to <hi>Big</hi> for you; and <hi>Burst</hi> out upon him, if you can <hi>Cope</hi> with him? And is his Name and Honor worth Nothing with you, who is Infinitely, more <hi>Regardable</hi> than Ten Thousand of us? O where is your Zeal and Fidelity to him, and to what your self do Profess, when you would be called his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> if you can see all Betrayed and Ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and be no more Touched, than if all were according to your Wishes? <hi>When one speaks Villany, another Laughs at it, a Third Defends it, who that is not all Earth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43562:26"/> can bear this? (Bp. Hall.)</hi> Is it Gods Cause only that makes you lukewarm and <hi>Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick?</hi> O Sir, when you but Remember, <hi>Who he is,</hi> Sure you will never think you can do enough for him, that is so Infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Good.</hi> And when you know what is most <hi>Grateful</hi> to him, and he has put it into your <hi>Power,</hi> will you refuse to do so much for him? After he has so De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himself to be most <hi>Jealous</hi> of his Glory, shall any thing be so Dear to you, as that which is so <hi>Tender</hi> to him? Can you Love him and Honor him, and yet signifie no Indignation against such as treat his Glorious Name with the greatest Contempt and Scorn? Can you <hi>Laugh</hi> at those that <hi>Grieve his Spirit?</hi> and make some of the Bitterest of his <hi>Foes</hi> your Intimate <hi>Friends?</hi> who but his <hi>Enemies take his Name in Vain?</hi> And shall such inherit your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and <hi>Caresses,</hi> as if they had done the most Obliging <hi>Meritorious</hi> Service, to throw Dirt at your <hi>Lord? Do you so Provoke the Lord to Jealousy?</hi> Is any better than He? And is that your Loving him above all, to <hi>prefer</hi> a Vile Sinner before him? Yea to take part with his very Enemies against him?</p>
            <p>Sir, We shall not find it enough in the great day of Final Accounts, to say, Lord
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43562:27"/> we have not <hi>Profaned</hi> thy Name. For he will tell us, I sent you into the World to <hi>Glorifie</hi> my Name upon Earth: And where you might, and would not, <hi>Stand</hi> up for me, you did <hi>Despise</hi> me. O then for Gods sake Sir, Appear in vindication of his <hi>Aspersed</hi> Honor, that when so Few care for it, or will do any thing in Faithfulness to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, He may give you that <hi>Elogium,</hi> Gen. 7.1. <hi>Thee have I seen Righteous before me in this Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. What will you do, Sir, for <hi>Christs</hi> sake, who pour'd out his very Hearts Blood for yours? Can you Forget or Slight him, who is your very <hi>Life</hi> and your only <hi>Hope?</hi> And make the Lightest account of his <hi>Love</hi> and his <hi>Death?</hi> Have you no more Kindness, nor Gratitude, or Honor for such a Friend? And how will you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press your Resentment of all his Astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Favours? Will you only give him a <hi>Jewish Hail,</hi> and the Lying Complement, to cry, <hi>Glory be to the Son,</hi> and pay your <hi>Nod</hi> to his Name, while you make but a Scorn of his Religion, and count his Yoke <hi>Intolerable, Not to Swear at all?</hi> But when he has so signified his Pleasure, can you love him; and yet take no Care to Promote it? You know, Sir, how <hi>Studious</hi> and forward true Love is always to Please. And I am
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43562:27"/> sure, you can never Gratifie and Pleasure a Greater and Better <hi>Friend.</hi> Were you no more than a private <hi>Christian,</hi> yet you were Oblig'd to do all that ever you could for <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> But when you are a Christian <hi>Magistrate,</hi> how Awkward Sir, will the Office sit upon you, if you can <hi>Tolerate</hi> and allow this most Unchristian Practice? And wear a <hi>Dignity</hi> under him, only to Oppose him? I say to <hi>Oppose</hi> him: For himself tells you <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.30. <hi>He that is not With me is Against me.</hi> And the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate that is a <hi>Swearer,</hi> or a <hi>Conniver</hi> at his Lords Dishonor, does only use the <hi>Advantage</hi> of his Place, to do a great deal more <hi>Mischeif</hi> to the Christian Religion, than otherwise he could ever have done. And I wonder how any such can ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to hear from their Judge at the last, <hi>Come ye Blessed of my Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly. Will you do nothing Sir, for your dear <hi>Countrey's</hi> Sake? When God has given you so Large a soul in other respects, will you not be so Publick-Spirited, to put in among the Worthy <hi>Patriots</hi> that greatly concern themselves in seeking the <hi>Common Good?</hi> And how can you better Promote it, than in helping to Redress that Cursed Grievance, under which the <hi>Land Mourns?</hi> And to Cure those Corrupt Members that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43562:28"/> are such a Shame and <hi>Plague</hi> to the Church? For what an insufferable Absurdity is it Sir, to Toss that Great Name in <hi>Common-Oaths,</hi> which we Invocate in our most <hi>Solemn Prayers?</hi> It is not to be endured in a <hi>Christian</hi> Community. It has too much and too long been let alone already; to our great Infamy and just Reproach. And an Odious Brand it would be upon us, were we no more than a <hi>Civilized,</hi> and not a Christian Nation. For the very <hi>Heathens</hi> would never Suffer the <hi>Gods</hi> whom they <hi>Worshipped,</hi> to be so Scorned and egregiously <hi>Vilified.</hi> This, this, Sir, is one of the Cursed things, for which the Lord hath a <hi>Controversy</hi> with us, and for which <hi>Wrath</hi> is gone out against us. And till it be cast out, O what Expectation, but of Fiery In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation! We Look for Peace and Good days, but, alas, Sir, what Peace and Good can the <hi>Toleration,</hi> of Ungodliness, and such <hi>Connivance</hi> at Gods High Dishonor <hi>Prognosticate?</hi> How can it consist with the Equity and Glory of God, to Espouse the Cause of an <hi>Incorrigible</hi> People, that <hi>go on still in their Trespasses,</hi> and even Justifie their Offences; as if they had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>Amiss,</hi> or had no <hi>Need</hi> to Turn and Alter their Course? Let our Cause be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so <hi>Right;</hi> tis much more Disgraced, than ever its li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be Promoted, by such
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43562:28"/> as think to Carry it with <hi>Hectoring</hi> and <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Damning.</hi> Yea even our Successes in the World, and the very Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of Heaven, will but help the faster to Undo us; as long as we continue in such a posture of <hi>Hostility</hi> against the Blessed Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>Indeed Guilt is not then <hi>National,</hi> nor so Crying, when there are strict Laws against it, and Magistrates and Ministers join their <hi>Forces</hi> to Curb and Disgrace it. But O how Rueful is the Prospect, Sir, when they on whom our Eyes are for <hi>Help,</hi> are False or Cold, and shew little Concern, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it be their <hi>Greivance</hi> and Spight at any thing that looks towards Amendment; And their Forwardness to stand in the <hi>Way</hi> of the Best Intentions, and <hi>Crush</hi> all Endeavours to do us Good? And are rather <hi>Deriders</hi> and Opposers of them, than any Well-willers or <hi>Contributers</hi> to Promote 'em. 'Twas <hi>Phineas</hi> his <hi>Standing up to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Judgment, that stopt the Plague. Psal.</hi> 106.30. And such now is our most Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Remedy, Sir, to do <hi>Justice</hi> upon No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Offenders, whose Crying Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will not Suffer the <hi>Sword</hi> of God's just Indignation to be put up into the <hi>Sheath.</hi> The Merciful God, who is loth to strike, even when Provoked, how
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43562:29"/> ready is he to hold his hand, upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion for it? O that we may not <hi>Hinder</hi> him of the Opportunity, so to shew his Mercy! May it not stick Sir, at your door, nor mine, that Wars do not <hi>Cease,</hi> and that we are not Blest with Sweet and <hi>Happy</hi> Days.</p>
            <p>You complain much of <hi>Perjury,</hi> that some who come before you seem not to Care what Oath they take. And if that be so, Good Sir, do what you can to Remove the Cause; And that is the <hi>Common-Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> which makes Consciences so <hi>Case-Hardened,</hi> they neither Tremble or Flinch even at the Nefandous Guilt of <hi>Forswear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> You seem much Concerned for the Land of your <hi>Nativity:</hi> And I really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you Desire to see it Prosper. And to this End, Give me leave to tell you Sir, you may Contribute yet a better Assistance, than with your <hi>Purse:</hi> What shall Cost you Less, yet will do us much more <hi>Good,</hi> yea and further Oblige us, to turn the Sword of <hi>Justice</hi> upon the <hi>Enemies of our own House,</hi> than to draw the <hi>Military</hi> Sword in open Field, against another En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emy. For what is it that so arms and strengthens them against us, as our own <hi>Enmity</hi> and Rebellion against Heaven? And therefore the more Instrumental you
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43562:29"/> are Sir, to Beat down that, the better <hi>Friend</hi> you must needs be to your Country, and the more <hi>Formidable</hi> to all our Infernal and Anti-Christian Foes, and follow the Likeliest Method to <hi>Suppress</hi> them. For this is to take away the very <hi>Ground</hi> of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that provokes the King of all the World, to make them his <hi>Scourge,</hi> to Correct us. And could we but thus Engage him to be <hi>with</hi> us, what need we Fear then who is <hi>against</hi> us?</p>
            <p>Fourthly. Will you shew your Esteem and Concern Sir, for <hi>Precious Souls,</hi> made after the <hi>Image</hi> of God, and that are the Price of his <hi>Son</hi>'s Blood, yea each of 'em more worth than a <hi>World?</hi> Can you see them sink and perish, and never Care for it? And when madly Running upon their own <hi>Damnation,</hi> will you do nothing to stop and Prevent them? When every Oath is as a <hi>Stab,</hi> and like so many <hi>Seals</hi> annex'd to the Deed of Conveyance, whereby they make themselves over into the <hi>Devils</hi> hands: (God having straightly Forbidden all the World, under Pain of Damnation, so to Meddle with his Tremendous <hi>Name.</hi>) And is this Charity and Loving our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Sincerely and Fervently; When you see them in a way that is so far from Good, Posting <hi>Hell-ward,</hi> and are for sending
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43562:30"/> them Packing, and <hi>Down with 'em?</hi> If not to <hi>Drink</hi> them down, yet to let them <hi>Swear</hi> themselves down, and you Laugh at the Sport, and Applaud the Humor? For ought I know Sir, The very <hi>Laughing</hi> at this Sin, has helped to lay many a Soul in <hi>Hell.</hi> Because they saw how the Humor took, and so many <hi>Oaths,</hi> so many <hi>Jests;</hi> Thus they were Tempted to make their Damnation your <hi>Recreation.</hi> And if this be your Kindness to your Friend, O what's your Cruelty to your worst Enemy! If to <hi>Suffer</hi> Sin upon your Brother, is to <hi>Hate him in your Heart;</hi> And if S. <hi>Johns Logick</hi> be good with you, that the <hi>Hatred</hi> of your Brother makes you a <hi>Murderer;</hi> Then by so <hi>Kind</hi> a Gentleman as you are Reputed Sir, I think this is fit to be considered. For all the Kindness of your <hi>House,</hi> will never Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensate for such Unmercifulness to <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be Sharp upon the Swearers Sir, you can never be Kinder to your Friends; Whether they be Guilty of this Wickedness, or not Guilty. If they will be so much their own, and Gods, and their Countrey's <hi>Enemies,</hi> to make themselves so Obnoxious; The best thing then you can do for 'em, is to go as far as ever the <hi>Laws</hi> will allow you, to reclaim 'em. But if they be of the other sort, that <hi>Hate</hi> the prophaneness, you
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43562:30"/> cannot oblige them more, than to shew your <hi>Concurrence</hi> with them, to save us all from such a Plague, that is the Bloody <hi>Bane</hi> of so many Souls.</p>
            <p>Fifthly. Give me leave to Argue with you Sir, a little from the Topick of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and to Sollicite you here to put forth your self with vigour, for your <hi>Credit</hi> Sake: That you may not bring your self under a just Suspicion, for no true Friend to Gods Honor; when you partially <hi>Lean</hi> to such, as nothing but Despise and Defy him. For but to <hi>Palliate</hi> the Corruption, betrays a man to be Rotten and Naught; That (if himself do not Practice it, yet) he can well enough <hi>away with it.</hi> And when he does not <hi>Abhor the Evil,</hi> a very Great man will make bold to tell him, <hi>There is no Fear of God before his eyes.</hi> Psal. 36, 1, 4. And indeed too much Suspicion do they give, that themselves are of the same <hi>Confederacy</hi> against Heaven, who will sooner side with the Swearer, than with the Reprover.</p>
            <p>Therefore though you may know too many Sir, who will be like to turn that to your <hi>Reproach,</hi> which is indeed your greatest Honor; Counting nothing more <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> than to be truly <hi>Conscientious;</hi> Yet I hope you will never make your self
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43562:31"/> really <hi>Vile,</hi> to come off the better with such Judges. As S. <hi>Aug.</hi> Confesses, Before he was a Christian, <hi>(Ego ne Vituperarer, Vitiosior fiebam.)</hi> I was the more Vicious, to save my <hi>Credit;</hi> Least I might be thought the more <hi>Abject,</hi> for being the more <hi>Innocent.</hi> And though some that Name the Name of <hi>Christ</hi> are Ashamed of him before men, and count it a <hi>Diminution</hi> to their Honor, to Stand up for <hi>His;</hi> Yet I hope Sir, you know a better way to <hi>Honor:</hi> And that nothing in the World does more really <hi>Recommend</hi> and Endear even the Noblest and the Greatest than their serious Piety, in Profoundly <hi>Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> God; and their mighty Usefulness, in doing abundance of <hi>Good</hi> to men. For what is true Honor, but the <hi>Rumor</hi> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions Pious and Good, rebounding from the Soul to the <hi>Notice</hi> of the World? And the highest <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> could never yet pretend to higher Titles, than <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Handmaids</hi> of the most <hi>High God.</hi> Who are really the most Honorable, but such as do the <hi>Worthiest</hi> things, and are most <hi>Considerable</hi> for that which is truly Great and Good? The <hi>Blustering</hi> Swearer then that would rudely snatch away Gods Honor, to adorn himself with the <hi>Spoils,</hi> gets only the Honor of a Notorious <hi>Rebel,</hi> and a bold <hi>Thief</hi> and <hi>Usurper.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:43562:31"/>
            <p>And such <hi>Scandalous</hi> Sinners do not only <hi>Ruine</hi> their own Reputation, but also help to bring a <hi>Blot</hi> even upon those with whom they are <hi>Intimate,</hi> to make the less Obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the worse thought of, for being any way concern'd among them. Here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir, it is adviseable, to take care of your <hi>own,</hi> as well as of <hi>God</hi>'s Honor. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in taking part with such as are out with him, you Pollute your own name; and by Inclining to such a <hi>Crew,</hi> expose your self to be Reputed no better than <hi>one of 'em:</hi> and nothing like the man whose heart is <hi>Right with God,</hi> and whom the <hi>King of Heaven will Honor.</hi> To put away from you then Sir, the reproach of being <hi>Gods</hi> Enemy, and a <hi>Traytor</hi> to Heaven; I know no better Expedient, than to shew you are Affected to his Honor, by your burning <hi>Zeal</hi> against all the Rude <hi>Violators</hi> of it. 'Till you are able to declare with the man after his own Heart, <hi>Psal.</hi> 139.31, 22. <hi>Do not I hate them, O Lord that hate thee? And am not I grieved with those that rise up against thee? I hate them with perfect Hatred, I count them my Enemies.</hi> No Enemies that give me more <hi>Disturbance,</hi> nor any to whom I have a greater <hi>Aversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Thus Sir, will you Interess your self in the <hi>Controversy</hi> of your Lords Honor; and never be Ashamed to take his Part,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43562:32"/> whose very meanest servants may make themselves <hi>Glorious,</hi> in being <hi>Zealous</hi> for his <hi>Glory?</hi> And how much more may you Ennoble your self, by Adorning the Noble <hi>Post</hi> you are in, and chusing rather to have it said of you, <q rend="margDblQuotes">He acts like a Good <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> a Worthy <hi>Magistrate,</hi> and a <hi>Brave</hi> man; so to Honor his God, and Oblige his Country; as the <hi>Favourite</hi> of Heaven, and the <hi>Darling</hi> of all Righteous men upon Earth: Than that the <hi>Character</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to another sort should be fit for your wearing, to be of such a Strein, That let Church and Souls, and the Glory of God Sink or Swim, he is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise taken up, than to Mind any such matters: Let Swearers pour out their Blasphemies, in his very <hi>Face,</hi> he has nothing to say against them, but will sooner partake with them, than, in any other way, <hi>Reflect</hi> upon 'em. He has no Zeal, but for his <hi>Lusts</hi> and his <hi>Sports:</hi> No Revenge, but for his own <hi>Petts</hi> and <hi>Quarrels.</hi> Such as are most out with God, find the best welcome with him: And the <hi>Godliness</hi> which he should help to <hi>Support,</hi> he <hi>Hates</hi> in his heart. Not a Child of God that he can abide:</q> But if youll' shew any <hi>Zeal</hi> for Gods Honor, you must never hope for his <hi>Favour.</hi> Alas, who can expect he should Correct that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43562:32"/> which is his own, not only <hi>Practice</hi> but <hi>Pastime?</hi> He will sooner Persecute Gods <hi>Servants,</hi> than Punish his <hi>Blasphemers.</hi> Let him get but any the least Advantage, he will take a Swinging <hi>Vengeance</hi> upon a Zealous Godly man; but struggle hard to help off the most <hi>Flagitious</hi> Offender, if he has but the good Hap, to be one of the Lewd <hi>Knot.</hi> Can you think it a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Sir, to have such a Report as this? I have more Charity for you, and cannot entertain so hard a thought of my Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Friend: God deliver you Sir, from that Honor. May your share be <hi>such Honor as have all God</hi>'s <hi>Saints.</hi> May he <hi>Love</hi> you and Good men <hi>Praise</hi> you: And then no matter tho the rest do not so well <hi>Approve</hi> of you.</p>
            <p>Sixthly. Let me also Plead with you, Sir, the Cause of the <hi>Poor</hi> and beseech you to do this Justice, for their Sakes. If you think it too mean for me to mention your own Worldly Interest, concern'd in the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture</hi> incurr'd, by your <hi>Wilfull and Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Omission,</hi> and neglecting to do it: For 'tis like you may most commonly Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape here; Though sometime it may be your Hap, to meet with such as shall Fear <hi>God,</hi> and the Rebukes of their own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences,</hi> more than your Displeasure;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43562:33"/> who will venture to go as far as the Law <hi>Authorises</hi> them, to make you <hi>Sensible</hi> of your Default. And then you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve to be called somewhat worse than a <hi>Sorry Husband,</hi> for Incurring the <hi>Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> rather than you would perform your Duty, and be seen to stand up in the <hi>Vindication,</hi> of God's Glory. But if you are careless of your own Profit Sir, or think that none will dare to touch you there: Yet sure you will not be a Defrauder and Oppressor of the <hi>Poor,</hi> instead of reaching out Kindness to 'em, to withold their own <hi>Right</hi> from 'em. Instead of <hi>Feeding</hi> the Hungry, and <hi>Cloathing</hi> the Naked; O do not <hi>Strip</hi> and <hi>Starve</hi> them; to Gratifie the Full and Wealthy, who in being <hi>Swearers,</hi> become the Poors <hi>Debtors.</hi> Help them at least to the share which belongs to 'em. That you may not have only the <hi>Precious Souls,</hi> which perish thro' your Fault, but the <hi>Poor-Bodys</hi> also, Pinch'd and Wrong'd by the same Neglect, to <hi>Cry</hi> against you.</p>
            <p>Seventhly. Be thus Just Sir, for your own <hi>Peace</hi> sake, that you may not go <hi>Self-tormented</hi> with a Guilty <hi>Consciousness</hi> of your own Falsehood to your <hi>Lord;</hi> Nor lye under his Frowns and the Dread of his Wrath, for <hi>Betraying</hi> your Trust and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43562:33"/>
               <hi>Deserting</hi> the cause which you were set up to Promote. I confess your Zeal in opposing the Enemies of Gods Glory may give you some more Trouble from without, than such do find, as more Consult their own <hi>Ease,</hi> than his <hi>Honor.</hi> But that trouble, Sir, will be more than <hi>Recompenced,</hi> by such a <hi>Peace</hi> within, as <hi>passes Understanding.</hi> When your Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence shall give you good words, and the <hi>Spirit of God witness with your Spirit, that you are the Child of God;</hi> Because so hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Concerned for the Honor of your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in Heaven.</hi> O Sir, the Light of his Countenance, the Tokens of his Love, and the Hope of his Glory, will give you that Heavenly Satisfaction, which shall make you slight all the <hi>Clamors</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions</hi> of obnoxious Sinners: and count such Peace with God no <hi>hard Bargain,</hi> tho Purchased with the <hi>Ill will</hi> of some men, that were never <hi>well affected</hi> to the Government of Heaven. O what can ever give you such a true, Noble, and Divine Pleasure, as to be like <hi>God</hi> himself; A <hi>Sanctuary</hi> to the Distressed, a <hi>Curb</hi> to the Wicked, and a <hi>Patron</hi> to the Good? <hi>Mens Conscia Recti,</hi> this is the <hi>Brazen Wall</hi> against all Assaults of Adverse Fortune in the present Life. And this will be the Comfort of a <hi>Dying Hour;</hi> such a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43562:34"/> Comfort as <hi>preponderates</hi> all the Pleasures of the Flesh, and the Joys of the World. When you have <hi>done Judgment and Justice,</hi> you may then with Confidence and Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in your God, address to the great <hi>Protector</hi> of such, as his holy Servant does; <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.121. <hi>Leave me not to my Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressors.</hi> O Remember, Sir, your Future Accounts, and what will bring you Peace at the <hi>Last,</hi> as well as make your Mind <hi>Serene,</hi> and Easie at Present. And that the <hi>Testimony of Conscience</hi> may be your <hi>Rejoycing,</hi> Dare to do your Duty, as an Upright and truly Worshipful <hi>Minister of Justice;</hi> Who are for Approving your self to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and for securing that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treasure, and <hi>Continual Feast</hi> within you, the Blessed <hi>Peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly. For <hi>Conscience</hi> sake, Sir, and in Pursuance of that Truth and Justice, which alone can make you deserve the Character of an <hi>Honest Worthy</hi> man: Remember the Obligation of your <hi>Vow</hi> in <hi>Baptism;</hi> when first you got the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Name, as the <hi>Faithful Soldier and Servant of Christ, Manfully to Fight the Battles of the Lord,</hi> against all the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his Honor. And also the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of your <hi>Oath</hi> in the <hi>Commission</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:43562:34"/> you have receiv'd, as a Magistrate, <hi>to do Right unto all, according to the Statutes of the Realm.</hi> And ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it appear, Sir, that you are a man of Conscience and Integrity, not to be <hi>Warpt</hi> with Fear or Favour, but set upon the Execution of <hi>Right,</hi> whoever stands in the way.</p>
            <p>Now here I ask you not, Sir, for a <hi>Courtesie;</hi> but a <hi>Debt;</hi> What you owe to the <hi>Publick,</hi> and to your own most So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Engagement.</hi> You have <hi>Sworn,</hi> Sir, and <hi>must</hi> Perform it. And I hope you will never add to the <hi>Perjuries,</hi> which your self Bewail; nor <hi>Falsify</hi> your sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oath, to Court any ones good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iking and Approbation; Nor for Dread of any ones Ill-will or Indignation. But let the <hi>Law</hi> have its Course, and the <hi>Justice</hi> which, thereafter, you are to Dispence, let it be done; whoever Scoff or Censure, whoever Grumble or Threaten. Consult not so much your own Carnal Ease, or Ill mens Frowns or Applause, as how you shall Answer it to God, and your own Conscience, in the Discharge of your <hi>Place;</hi> and in Faithfulness to the <hi>Depositum</hi> entrusted into your hands. To <hi>Betray</hi> which were a Wrong, not only to your own <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> but to him whom you <hi>Represent,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:43562:35"/> and to All for whom you are bound to do <hi>Justice,</hi> according to your Skil and Power. You are a <hi>Guardian</hi> of the Laws, Sir, to keep them, as far as you can, from being <hi>violated</hi> and Wrong'd: And also the <hi>Steward,</hi> to Distribute out to every one that <hi>Portion</hi> which the Laws allot them. Such, you know, Sir, is your weighty <hi>Charge:</hi> and <hi>Faithfulness</hi> here will be your greatest <hi>Praise.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Execution of <hi>Laws,</hi> which are not all Equal, but greatly <hi>Differ,</hi> according to their Subject-matter, 'Twill be no <hi>Partiality</hi> more than is Praiseworthy, if you think your self concerned and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd, to have respect unto those Laws, in the first place, which set <hi>Entrenchments</hi> and Fences to secure the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, and make Provision for the <hi>Exercise</hi> of his holy Religion. For such Laws are only some new Enforcements of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine;</hi> whereby you are <hi>Antecedently</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, <hi>truely and Indifferently to Minister Justice, to the Punishment of Wickedness and Vice; and to the Maintenance of God</hi>'s <hi>true Religion and Vertue: And above all things, to Seek his Honor and Glory. Study<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to preserve the people under your Inspection, not only in Wealth and Peace, but also in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:43562:35"/>
            <p>Lastly, Sir, Look narrowly to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of your Office, especially in the suppression of ungodliness and the Encouragement of Good Manners, for your own <hi>Salvation</hi> Sake: That you may not pull down the Guilt of others <hi>Bloud</hi> upon your own Head, and be charged with the Sins, which you should and might have <hi>Hindred:</hi> Nor yet fall under the Doom of the wicked and <hi>Slothful</hi> Servant, for neglecting to trade with the <hi>Talents</hi> put into your hands, for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your <hi>Lord.</hi> You make the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness your <hi>own,</hi> which you bear witness to, <hi>Uncorrected:</hi> And you <hi>Allow,</hi> what you do not <hi>Punish.</hi> O Remember, Sir, what a Judgment the Lord did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce upon <hi>Eli</hi>'s house, at which 'twas said, <hi>Both the ears of him that heard it should Tingle.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11. And what was the Reason for it, but <hi>because his Sons made themselves vile, and he Restrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them not.</hi> ver. 13. The Swearers Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, 'tis true, is <hi>their own,</hi> and they make themselves <hi>vile:</hi> But the Guilt of not <hi>Restraining</hi> them as you ought, will lie heavy upon you, and for that you you must look to <hi>Answer.</hi> Tho it be a Negative thing, and but an <hi>Omission.</hi> to be so slack and Remiss; One of the sharpest curses in the Bible is for an <hi>Omission. Judg.</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43562:36"/> 5.23. <hi>Curse ye Meroz, said the Angel of the Lord, Curse ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof.</hi> And why so severe an <hi>Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Not because they Fought against the Lord: But because they did not <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spouse</hi> his Cause, to Fight his Battails against his Provoking Enemies: <hi>They came not to the Help of the Lord against the Mighty.</hi> O may you hear and fear so to <hi>Tempt</hi> the Lord your God, and to Provoke his <hi>Jealousie,</hi> by your Carelesness of his Glory.</p>
            <p>Remember, Good Sir, how short your time is; And how soon the Part you have to Act on the present <hi>Stage</hi> will be at an end; And that your Eternal State in another World will be <hi>Determined,</hi> thereafter as you now Acquit your self in this. And having Death, and the great Judgment, and Everlasting Life in your eye, O be not in such Care to curry Favour with <hi>Men,</hi> as to Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate your self with your <hi>Judge,</hi> and so to Negotiate for his Honor and Interests; That you may hear from him, at the Finishing of your Course, that <hi>Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> Sentence, which will be more worth than a <hi>World:</hi> And that after you have been Instrumental to <hi>turn many to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness,</hi> you may <hi>Shine as the Stars in the Kingdom of your Father for ever and ever.</hi> Your great Business in this World, Sir,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43562:36"/> is not to Please <hi>men,</hi> or to Please your <hi>Flesh,</hi> but to Please and Glorifie <hi>God,</hi> and save your <hi>Soul.</hi> And should you Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry and Perish, Alas, what Good would the Good thoughts of a Multitude of the <hi>Damned</hi> Creatures do you? Sure you can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think that the Partaking of their Sins, will be any <hi>Valuable Consideration,</hi> for sharing in their Plagues: Nor that Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or Holding with the Ungodly Crew in their wild <hi>Risques,</hi> and Extravagancies of Living, is the way to be <hi>Numbered with Gods Saints in Glory everlasting.</hi> O Sir, you know who has told us, <hi>That Narrow is the way thither, and few find it:</hi> and those Few that Enter, must <hi>Strive</hi> for it. And pray Sir, what Striving is that, to Swim with the <hi>Stream</hi> of Flesh and Blood, after the <hi>Course</hi> of the World, and to do as the <hi>Most,</hi> and serve God only with that which puts us to no <hi>Expence?</hi> To Shrink from all <hi>Trouble</hi> for his Sake and not so much as <hi>venture</hi> to Displease a Wicked <hi>Swearer?</hi> If this will serve the Turn, we may say then, <hi>Wide is the Way to Heaven, who can miss it?</hi> O may you never venter your dear Immortal Soul, Sir, in such a <hi>Way,</hi> nor run your Everlasting Salvation into these Despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>Hazards.</hi> But so Concern, and Bestir your self, to Vindicate your Lord's
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43562:37"/>
               <hi>Right's,</hi> and to bring him <hi>Glory;</hi> That your Case may look Hopeful indeed for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and you may be like one that shall dwell in his <hi>Holy Hill,</hi> and Inherit the Blessed things Inconceivable, which <hi>God has prepared for them that Love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, if there be any <hi>Weight</hi> in what I have here offer'd, Consider it, I beseech you, without Reflection on the <hi>Unworthy</hi> hand, from whence it comes. And reject it not under the Scornful name of <hi>Preaching;</hi> When 'tis not only the <hi>Parsons,</hi> with their old story; but <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> who Quicken and Oblige us now to make the <hi>Quarterly Pay</hi> to our People; to save their <hi>Purses from</hi> the Penalty, and their <hi>Souls</hi> from a worse Punishment. That we might not be thought to do it only <hi>Pro Forma,</hi> from the Pulpit, to fill up the Hour; The Nobles and Worthies who Constitute the the Highest <hi>Court</hi> in the Land, have (under the <hi>Kings</hi> most Excellent Majesty,) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpos'd their <hi>Authority;</hi> That where our words were <hi>Despised, Penalties</hi> might be Inflicted. And you Sir, are one of their <hi>Trustees</hi> and <hi>Executors,</hi> to see their Laws put in Force, and their Pleasure fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And after such Provision made, shall Blasphemy still play the <hi>Bear,</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> amongst us, and none to stop
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43562:37"/> the <hi>Outrage?</hi> shall the <hi>Flouds of Ungodly men</hi> make you so <hi>Afraid,</hi> that your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance is rather to <hi>Hide</hi> your self, than to Discharge your <hi>Office?</hi> And will you be Poor and <hi>Timerous</hi> in Heaven's Cause, where you should be <hi>Bold as a Lion?</hi> seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to own a <hi>Guilt,</hi> where you are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercising one of the greatest <hi>Uertues?</hi> O Sir, call up your Zeal and Courage here, and make some brave <hi>Efforts,</hi> to shew your self, <hi>Worthy</hi> of your self. The Sword which God has put into your hands, <hi>Dare</hi> to turn it against them, who <hi>Dare</hi> to turn their Tongues against him. And in standing up as one of the <hi>Avengers</hi> of such Horrid Crimes Raging among us, you will Interpose as one of the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers,</hi> to keep off the Judgments they are pulling down upon us. While you have no part or Lot with those <hi>Betrayers</hi> of our Government and Religion, who would make the <hi>Good Law,</hi> even Good for <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet after all, let me add, Sir, That where other means will serve the turn, It will not argue your Injustice, but rather Commend your Prudence, to <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persede</hi> this: So that the <hi>End</hi> of the Law be but Answer'd. For what a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sort of <hi>Christians</hi> are they, (and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43562:38"/> no better than <hi>Pagans</hi> under the Christian Name,) that cannot forbear <hi>Swearing,</hi> but for fear of <hi>Paying?</hi> They are the Wild <hi>Beasts</hi> of the people who are to feel the <hi>Curb</hi> and the <hi>Lash,</hi> and they to be Hamper'd with such <hi>Laws of men,</hi> that shew nothing of Conscience or Regard to the Holy <hi>Law of God.</hi> All sincere Christians are a <hi>Law</hi> to themselves, and such towards God in the very Secret of their hearts, that his Fear and Love, and their own Consciences and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, are a greater <hi>Restraint,</hi> and a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Guide</hi> to them, than all the Commands and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Men.</p>
            <p>But such as are not otherwise to be dealt with, 'Tis fit the <hi>Law</hi> should have its <hi>Force</hi> upon 'em. For <hi>Execution</hi> is the <hi>Life</hi> of Laws. And the present Law was not intended only to be Derided and Trampled, as a <hi>Toothless</hi> thing, that could not Fasten upon Offenders. Nor to lie by <hi>Dormant</hi> and Idle, as if there were no such thing at all, to Reduce those to some better Manners, whom nothing else would Restrain, from Flying at God, and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing their <hi>Neighbours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Great <hi>God</hi> Bless this, and all Means of every sort, to do us Good. And the Blessing of Heaven be their Portion,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43562:38"/> who shall Prudently and Faithfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern themselves to help forward a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reformation, particularly of this <hi>Provoking Abomination.</hi> Amongst which best of all our <hi>Benefactors,</hi> may you Sir, be as <hi>Willing</hi> as God has made you <hi>Able,</hi> with good Effect, to concern your self O Rise up, like one Awaking out of Sleep, and shake off that <hi>Sluggishness</hi> to Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Gods Glory, which still, (as a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy <hi>Clog,</hi>) holds down so many. And go forth like a man of <hi>Conscience</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> to do things Worthy of your <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Place.</hi> And that you may Proceed on with all Happy Success, and find the Work <hi>Prosper</hi> in your hands, <hi>the Lord be with you,</hi> and Guide and Quicken and Enable you for the <hi>Office</hi> lying upon you; To Accomplish your <hi>Warfare,</hi> as his Faithful <hi>Soldier.</hi> That your <hi>Lord</hi> when he comes, may find you <hi>So Doing.</hi> And then <hi>Blessed</hi> shall you be; and in good time, <hi>Rest from your Labours:</hi> and at last, Receive the <hi>Honor</hi> without any <hi>Burden;</hi> and see the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, without any <hi>Clouds</hi> upon it; In that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Glory, where all that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>Serv'd</hi> him, shall Eternally <hi>Rejoyce</hi> in him, and <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Reign</hi> most Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43562:39"/>
            <p>I Beg your Pardon Sir, for the long <hi>Trouble,</hi> I have now given you; And that you will be pleas'd to Favour me with so much of the <hi>Candor</hi> and Kindness I have ever found with you, as to Accept this <hi>Pathetick</hi> Epistle, for the Expression of my <hi>Desire</hi> to Approve my Self,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours in all Thankfulness and Humble Service,</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:43562:39"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge <hi>13.</hi> Line <hi>26.</hi> for too Read so. p. <hi>17.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for wedded r. weeded. p. <hi>19.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> for your r. the. p. <hi>22.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> for tenure r. tenor. p. <hi>23.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> for sour r. sowr. p. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>28.</hi> for thee r. them. p. <hi>35.</hi> l. <hi>11.</hi> r. crooked. p. <hi>36.</hi> l. <hi>20.</hi> r. that Singularity p. <hi>40.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> r. serves. p. <hi>47.</hi> l. <hi>14.</hi> dele so. l. <hi>23.</hi> dissemble. p. <hi>49.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> r. sake. l. <hi>18.</hi> r. sakes. p. <hi>15.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> r. Horrid. p. <hi>23.</hi> l. <hi>14.</hi> r. Bedlam. p. <hi>27.</hi> l. <hi>29.</hi> r. Potsheard, and Potsheards. p. <hi>29.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi> for it r. that. p. <hi>30.</hi> l. <hi>23.</hi> for stout r. foul. p. <hi>40.</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> dele our. p. <hi>48.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> for your r. the. p. <hi>61.</hi> l. <hi>18.</hi> shew how well.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>